<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>talks on Cairo NLP</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/talks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in talks on Cairo NLP</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>cairo.nlp.group@gmail.com (cAIro|NLP Group)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>cairo.nlp.group@gmail.com (cAIro|NLP Group)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/talks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Arabic NLP Tools and Datasets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/talks/talk_2/jarrar_talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cairo.nlp.group@gmail.com (cAIro|NLP Group)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/talks/talk_2/jarrar_talk/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Overview of open-source tools and datasets developed for Arabic morphology analysis, Arabic dialects, lexicographic databases, named entity recognition, relation and event extraction, word sense disambiguation, semantic analysis, synonym generation, hate speech detection, LLM instruction and benchmarking datasets, among others&#xA;Speaker Bio Professor of Artificial Intelligence and the director of SinaLab for Computational Linguistics and Artificial Intelligence at both, Hamad Bin Khalifa University/Qatar and Birzeit University/Palestine.&#xA;Recording </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with LLMs and RAG</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/talks/talk_1/hassan_talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cairo.nlp.group@gmail.com (cAIro|NLP Group)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/talks/talk_1/hassan_talk/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Large Language Models (LLMs) have revolutionized natural language processing, but they face challenges with hallucination and outdated knowledge. This introductory talk explores Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) as a solution that combines the reasoning capabilities of LLMs with real-time information retrieval from external knowledge sources. Perfect for beginners wanting to understand the RAG paradigm and experienced developers looking to implement their first RAG application.&#xA;Speaker Bio Hassan is Senior Applied Scientist at Microsoft, with more than 6 years of experience within NLP and AI across multilple locations along with Egypt, US, UK and Canada.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
